<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | Fugitive.ink(C)]]></title>
  <link href="http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-17T12:19:48-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rayyan Kamal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Autodidact's Approach]]></title>
    <link href="http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/blog/2014/09/17/an-autodidacts-approach/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-17T14:06:24-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/blog/2014/09/17/an-autodidacts-approach</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><html></p>

<p>In my last post, I addressed what my incentive was for deferring my medical education.  From there, I proceeded to list some of my weaknesses and strengths in order to lay the groundwork for my explorations within' the year.  Now that the groundwork has been laid, what have I done with the last four months to explore my inquiries and grow as a human being?  ...Well... Hopefully <i>something</i>!</p>




<p>Naturally, my first schematic for self-studying and exploration was very scheduled and quite similar to what you might experience in college or any other institutionalized setting.  I first identified areas of study that would address my weaknesses and peak my interest.  Then, I proceeded to write a schedule where I treated Monday-Friday as a 40 hour work week for my explorations -oh the wonders of savings and not needing to be employed.  Below is an example of what my schedule resembled:</p>




<p><b>EVERYDAY:</b></p>


<p>Music: Jazz theory, Trumpet, Guitar [1.5 hours a day | One instrument a day]</p>


<p>Physical/Mental: Parkour, Method of Loci [1.5 hours a day | Pick one]</p>




<p><b>ONE OF TWO BELOW EVERY WEEKDAY:</b></p>


<p>Fine arts: Drawing, Anatomy [2 hours every other day | Switch between Anatomy & Drawing]</p>


<p>Awareness: History, Political Ideology Research [2 hours on the days with no fine arts]</p>




<p><b>ONE OF TWO BELOW EVERY WEEKDAY:</b></p>


<p>Programming/Mathematics: Raspberry Pi, Networking, Python, R [2.5 hours a day]</p>


<p>Social Intelligence/Engineering: Research on body language and behavioral science [2.5 hours a day]</p>




<p><b>MONTHLY:</b></p>


<p>Self-awareness: Blogging [1 post per month]</p>




<p>So now, four months later, how has this curriculum gone?  Just as I should have suspected institutionalized education would go.  My schedule has been great for learning a vast amount of material in a short amount of time, but in terms of fulfillment and satisfaction, it has been quite lacking.  How can that be if I spend most of my days studying what I want?</p>




<p><b>The answer</b>: With such a set schedule and institutional feel, there still feels like a sense of requirement and ranking rather than pure enjoyment.  My incentives get skewed towards learning a lot for some image I have rather than the true fulfillment of exploration.</p>




<p>When I was at the University of Kansas, I learned the most when a subject engaged me and I had room to practice it rather than worrying about what grade I got or how it would benefit my future career goals.  You know our current educational model is tainted when the incentive to learn is based on capital and job prospects rather than curiosity and vocation.  With that said, how do I reformulate my curriculum to be more satisfying?  Why did I choose this model in the first place?</p>




<p>Well, the reason I chose the institutionalized model has a simple answer: <b>It's the main paradigm of education that I know!</b>  I've been socialized since a child by the methodologies of the US school system and that makes it hard for me to escape.  Perhaps this is part of my growth?  I'm learning how to learn as an autonomous being free from the restrictions of our current education system... <i>At least for now</i>.</p>




<p>Now, for the more important question.  I believe the way for me to make a more satisfying curriculum for myself is to base my education on goals and what I accomplish rather than what I should be doing.  My autodidactic incentives are based in curiosity rather than societal expectations, and as such, I should be praising my self on what I accomplish rather than bogging down on what I have to do.  So based on my weaknesses/strength and subjects of interest, what are my goals?</p>




<ol>
<li>I want to feel physically empowered as well as know how my mind works.</li>
<li>Musically, I want to be able to play bebop jazz and apply it to many different genres.  Specifically, I want to be more proficient than I am now on guitar and trumpet.</li>
<li>For medical school and for my own personal aesthetic desires, I want to learn to draw so I can sketch what I see quickly.</li>
<li>I want to be more articulate on points in politics and social justice issues.  I want to learn more about Anarchism and history, both US and World History.</li>  
<li>I want to indulge in technological pursuits by learning about Linux, the Raspberry Pi, Python and computer networking.</li>
<li>There will always be a place in my heart for mathematics, and as such I would like to gain a stronger grasp on statistics and analysis.</li>
<li>There's a lot of value as a future physician in being able to understand humans on both a intellectual and emotional level.  I hope to learn more about human body language and behavior in order to better understand my friends, family, romantic partners, acquaintances and future patients.</li>
</ol>




<p>Now that my goals have been listed, how can I approach these goals without having a rigorous schedule?  I first need to identify which goals require regular practice.  Subjects like music and physical fitness require regular practice in order to progress.  I just need to remember that progressing here shouldn't feel obligatory but rather motivated by curiosity.  If at anytime it feels driven by a sense of necessity, then I need to re-evaluate why I'm practicing regularly. With every other subject listed, as long as I engage in one of those activities daily and make more specific, concrete goals, there's no reason I need a detailed schedule.  I have a basic schedule now that is not hard set.  It's more based on immediate interest rather than a sense of obligation.</p>




<p>As I continue through my new curriculum, I need be open towards changing at anytime.  Perhaps the perfect system for an autodidact is based on constant adaptation?  I'm starting to think so.  I also need to make sure that every activity I engage in has a communal aspect/lab portion to it.  I need people to talk to, practice with and engage with if I'm looking to really learn and retain what I learn.</p>


<p></p>

<p>And with that, let the journey continue!</p>


<br />


<p>On performing a perfect central line installation: “I still have no idea what I did differently that day.  But from then on, my lines went in.  Practice is funny that way.  For days and days, you make out only the fragments of what to do.  And then one day you've got the thing whole.  Conscious learning become unconscious knowledge, and you cannot say precisely how.” -Atul Gawande</p>


<p></html></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Soliloquy of an Aspiring Physician]]></title>
    <link href="http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/blog/2014/04/29/Soliloquy-of-an-Aspiring-Physician/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T00:39:03-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/blog/2014/04/29/Soliloquy-of-an-Aspiring-Physician</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><html>
<body></p>

<pre><code>&lt;p&gt;In March of this year, I was notified of my acceptance into KU School of Medicine.  I believe most people would be ecstatic at the opportunity.  To have spent so many years in pursuit of medicine and to finally receive validation that you are wanted is something that every pre-medical student desires.  But, something felt off.  At first, I couldn't pin-point it because I too was soaking in the rays of validation and acceptance.  I mean, graduating with a 3.34 GPA and 29 MCAT isn't the most comforting feeling when applying for medical school, so to receive an acceptance letter my first try indeed caught me off guard.  After letting the excitement wear off, I realized that I was not ready for medical school.  Upon realizing this, I asked KU for a year deferment, which was granted.  A year outside of academia... What does that even look like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entering medical school this July wouldn't have been a mistake, since I believe I'm intellectually capable of being a medical student.  My main concern is that I'm not grounded as an individual.  The reason I know this is because I know exactly who I want to be -OK, it might change...  &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt;- and that image is incongruent with who I am now.  I realize that we shape into who we are over a lifetime, but I've been in school most of my life and a year outside of school will help me shape into the person I want to be before entering medical school.  Well, that begs the question.  Who do I want to be?  What does this person look like and what are they capable of?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better understand my ideal self, I want to make a list of my &lt;b&gt;weaknesses&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I can be quite flaky.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm intellectually dishonest at times about what I don't know.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Being intellectually dishonest has led me to become more arrogant over the years.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm impatient.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;When working on a long-term project, I often have poor follow through.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I don't have enough skepticism in my own ideals and opinions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm very bad at accepting affirmations about my character.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I exhibit false humility at times.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I jump to conclusions quickly only to find out my assumptions are often false.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Often, I do certain activities based on ego rather than interest.&lt;/li&gt;      
&lt;/ul&gt;   
In order to begin improving on my weaknesses, I also need to make a list of my &lt;b&gt;strengths&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm a quick learner.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;When motivated and inspired, I'm extremely reliable and, in general, much more articulate.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Inline with learning quickly, I often attempt to address conflict and my weaknesses as soon as they are apparent.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm relatively organized... When I want to be! &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm not very neurotic.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I exhibit an extremely high degree of optimism for the human race.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;When not stuck in my own arrogance, I am often able to navigate other people's dilemmas.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm extremely analytical, which makes me a very good puzzle solver -As long as the puzzle is also analytical in nature.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm able to talk and relate to most people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the lists above, what actions can I take towards addressing my weaknesses and nurturing my strengths?  By answering this question, I will be shaping how my year before entering medical school will look.  My first step towards doing this is by creating this blog!  I think articulating my thoughts through writing will help me understand what I'm trying to do while at the same time keeping me accountable.  I plan for each post to be insight into how I'm doing with my personal growth as an intelligent, emotional and dynamic human being.  Some posts will be more focused than others, but by having this outlet, I plan on grounding myself.  Once grounded, the possibilities are endless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>&ldquo;May I never see in the patient anything but a fellow creature in pain.&rdquo; -Oath of Maimonides
</p>
</body>
</html></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
