<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | Fugitive.ink(C)]]></title>
  <link href="http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-12T11:20:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rayyan Kamal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Soliloquy of an Aspiring Physician]]></title>
    <link href="http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/blog/2014/04/29/Soliloquy-of-an-Aspiring-Physician/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T00:39:03-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://fugitiveinkc.github.io/blog/2014/04/29/Soliloquy-of-an-Aspiring-Physician</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><html>
<body></p>

<pre><code>&lt;p&gt;In March of this year, I was notified of my acceptance into KU School of Medicine.  I believe most people would be ecstatic at the opportunity.  To have spent so many years in pursuit of medicine and to finally receive validation that you are wanted is something that every pre-medical student desires.  But, something felt off.  At first, I couldn't pin-point it because I too was soaking in the rays of validation and acceptance.  I mean, graduating with a 3.34 GPA and 29 MCAT isn't the most comforting feeling when applying for medical school, so to receive an acceptance letter my first try indeed caught me off guard.  After letting the excitement wear off, I realized that I was not ready for medical school.  Upon realizing this, I asked KU for a year deferment, which was granted.  A year outside of academia... What does that even look like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entering medical school this July wouldn't have been a mistake, since I believe I'm intellectually capable of being a medical student.  My main concern is that I'm not grounded as an individual.  The reason I know this is because I know exactly who I want to be -OK, it might change...  &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt;- and that image is incongruent with who I am now.  I realize that we shape into who we are over a lifetime, but I've been in school most of my life and a year outside of school will help me shape into the person I want to be before entering medical school.  Well, that begs the question.  Who do I want to be?  What does this person look like and what are they capable of?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better understand my ideal self, I want to make a list of my &lt;b&gt;weaknesses&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I can be quite flaky.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm intellectually dishonest at times about what I don't know.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Being intellectually dishonest has led me to become more arrogant over the years.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm impatient.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;When working on a long-term project, I often have poor follow through.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I don't have enough skepticism in my own ideals and opinions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm very bad at accepting affirmations about my character.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I exhibit false humility at times.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I jump to conclusions quickly only to find out my assumptions are often false.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Often, I do certain activities based on ego rather than interest.&lt;/li&gt;      
&lt;/ul&gt;   
In order to begin improving on my weaknesses, I also need to make a list of my &lt;b&gt;strengths&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm a quick learner.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;When motivated and inspired, I'm extremely reliable and, in general, much more articulate.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Inline with learning quickly, I often attempt to address conflict and my weaknesses as soon as they are apparent.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm relatively organized... When I want to be! &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm not very neurotic.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I exhibit an extremely high degree of optimism for the human race.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;When not stuck in my own arrogance, I am often able to navigate other people's dilemmas.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm extremely analytical, which makes me a very good puzzle solver -As long as the puzzle is also analytical in nature.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I'm able to talk and relate to most people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the lists above, what actions can I take towards addressing my weaknesses and nurturing my strengths?  By answering this question, I will be shaping how my year before entering medical school will look.  My first step towards doing this is by creating this blog!  I think articulating my thoughts through writing will help me understand what I'm trying to do while at the same time keeping me accountable.  I plan for each post to be insight into how I'm doing with my personal growth as an intelligent, emotional and dynamic human being.  Some posts will be more focused than others, but by having this outlet, I plan on grounding myself.  Once grounded, the possibilities are endless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>&ldquo;May I never see in the patient anything but a fellow creature in pain.&rdquo; -Oath of Maimonides
</p>
</body>
</html></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
